I am a vicar in the Church of England.
أنا كاهن في كنيسة انجلترا.
I've been a priest in the Church for 20 years.
وأنا قس في الكنيسة منذ عشرين عاماً.
For most of that time, I've been struggling and grappling
خلال أغلب هذه السنين, كنت أتصارع
with questions about the nature of God. Who is God?
مع أسئلة عن طبيعة الرب. من هو الرب؟
And I'm very aware that when you say the word "God,"
وأنا مدرك تماماً أنك حين تقول كلمة الرب,
many people will turn off immediately.
سيتحول عنك الكثير من الناس على الفور
And most people, both within and outside the organized church,
وأنه لايزال لدى أغلب الناس سواء داخل أو خارج الكنيسة
still have a picture of a celestial controller,
صورة عن حاكم سماوي
a rule maker, a policeman in the sky who orders everything,
مشرع للقواعد, شرطي في السماء يأمر كل شيء,
and causes everything to happen.
ويسبب حدوث كل شيء.
He will protect his own people,
وهو يحمي أتباعه,
and answer the prayers of the faithful.
ويجيب دعاء المؤمنين به.
And in the worship of my church,
وفي الصلاة بكنيستي,
the most frequently used adjective about God is "almighty."
تعد أكثر صفات الرب استخداماً هي "القدير"
But I have a problem with that.
لكنني أجد مشكلة في ذلك.
I have become more and more uncomfortable
لقد أصبحت غير مستريح أكثر وأكثر
with this perception of God over the years.
بشأن هذا المفهوم عن الرب على مر السنين.
Do we really believe that God is the kind of male boss that we've been presenting
هل تؤمن حقاً بأن الله هو ذلك القائد الذكر الذي كنا نقف أمامه
in our worship and in our liturgies over all these years?
في عبادتنا وشعائرنا على مر هذه السنين؟
Of course, there have been thinkers
بالطبع, هناك مفكرون
who have suggested different ways of looking at God.
اقترحوا طرقاً مختلفة للتفكير في الرب.
Exploring the feminine, nurturing side of divinity.
مستكشفين الجانب الأنثوي الحنون من الألوهية.
Suggesting that God expresses Himself or Herself through powerlessness,
مقترحين أن الرب يعبر عن نفسه من خلال الاستكانة,
rather than power.
أكثر مما يفعل من خلال القوة.
Acknowledging that God is unknown and unknowable by definition.
مقرين بأن الرب غير معروف ولا يمكن معرفته بطبيعة الحال.
Finding deep resonances with other religions and philosophies
وقد لاحظوا وجود تشابهات عميقة مع الأديان والفلسفات الأخرى
and ways of looking at life as part of what is a universal and global search for meaning.
وطرق النظر للحياة باعتبارها جزء من بحث كوني وعالمي عن تفسيرات.
These ideas are well known in liberal academic circles,
إن هذه الأفكار معروفة بشكل جيد في الأوساط الأكاديمية المتحررة,
but clergy like myself have been reluctant to air them,
لكن رجال الدين من أمثالي كانوا مترددين بشأن إعلانها,
for fear of creating tension and division in our church communities,
خوفاً من خلق توتر وفرقة في مجتمعاتنا الكنسية,
for fear of upsetting the simple faith of more traditional believers.
خوفاً من تثبيط إيمان المؤمنين من الناس العاديين.
I have chosen not to rock the boat.
لقد اخترت ألا أتسبب في جلبة.
Then, on December 26th last year, just two months ago,
ثم -في السادس والعشرين من ديسمبر السنة الماضية- أي قبل شهرين فقط,
that underwater earthquake triggered the tsunami.
أدى الزلزال الذي حدث تحت الماء هذا إلى تسونامي
And two weeks later, Sunday morning, 9th of January,
وبعدها بأسبوعين, في صباح الأحد التاسع من يناير,
I found myself standing in front of my congregation --
وجدت نفسي واقفاً أمام المصلين,
intelligent, well meaning, mostly thoughtful Christian people --
مسيحيون عميقو التفكير على الأغلب, حسنو النية. أذكياء,
and I needed to express, on their behalf, our feelings and our questions.
وكنت محتاجاً لأن أعبر بالنيابة عنهم عن مشاعرنا وأسئلتنا.
I had my own personal responses, but I also have a public role,
كانت لدي ردودي الخاصة, لكن كان لدي دور عام أقوم به أيضاً.
and something needed to be said.
وكان ينبغي أن أقول شيئاً.
And this is what I said.
وهذا هو ما قلته.
Shortly after the tsunami I read a newspaper article
بعد التسونامي بفترة قصيرة قرأت مقالاً في صحيفة
written by the Archbishop of Canterbury -- fine title --
كتبها رئيس أساقفة كانتربيري -وهو منصب رفيع-
about the tragedy in Southern Asia.
عن المأساة التي حدثت في جنوب آسيا.
The essence of what he said was this:
وكان خلاصة ما قال كالتالي:
the people most affected by the devastation and loss of life
إن الناس الأكثر تأثراً بهذا الخراب وبخسائر الأرواح
do not want intellectual theories about how God let this happen.
لا يرغبون في سماع نظريات فكرية عن سماح الرب بحدوث هذه المأساة.
He wrote, "If some religious genius did come up with an explanation
لقد كتب قائلاً: وإذا ما خرج علينا رجل دين عبقري بتفسير
of exactly why all these deaths made sense,
للسبب الذي حدثت من أجله كل هذه الوفيات,
would we feel happier, or safer, or more confident in God?"
هل سنشعر بأننا أكثر سعادة أو أمناً أو ثقة في الرب؟"
If the man in the photograph that appeared in the newspapers,
لو وقف الرجل الموجود في الصورة التي ظهرت بالصحف,
holding the hand of his dead child was standing in front of us now,
وهو ممسك بيد طفله الميت, أمامنا الآن,
there are no words that we could say to him.
فلن تكون هناك كلمات يمكننا أن نقولها له.
A verbal response would not be appropriate.
لن تكون الاستجابة اللفظية أمراً مناسباً.
The only appropriate response would be a compassionate silence
الاستجابة المناسبة الوحيدة ستكون الصمت مع التعاطف
and some kind of practical help.
وتقديم نوع من المساعدة العملية.
It isn't a time for explanation, or preaching, or theology;
لن يكون هذا وقت للتفسير أو الوعظ أو للحديث في علم اللاهوت,
it's a time for tears.
إنه وقت للدموع
This is true. And yet here we are, my church in Oxford,
هذا صحيح. مع هذا ها نحن في كنيستي في أكسفورد
semi-detached from events that happened a long way away,
شبه منفصلين عن الأحداث التي حدثت بعيداً جداً,
but with our faith bruised.
لكن إيماننا قد تأثر.
And we want an explanation from God.
ونحتاج إلى تفسير من الرب
We demand an explanation from God.
إننا نطلب تفسيراً من الرب.
Some have concluded that we can only believe in a God who shares our pain.
لقد انتهى البعض إلى أننا يجب أن نؤمن فقط في رب يشاركنا آلامنا.
In some way, God must feel the anguish, and grief,
ينبغي أن يشعر الرب بطريقة ما بالعذاب, والكمد,
and physical pain that we feel.
والألم الجسدي الذي نشعر به.
In some way the eternal God must be able to enter into the souls of human beings
بطريقة ما, ينبغي أن يكون الرب الخالد قادراً على الدخول إلى أرواح البشر
and experience the torment within.
وأن يشعر بالحرقة الموجودة داخلها.
And if this is true, it must also be that God knows the joy and exaltation
وإذا كان هذا صحيحاً, فلابد أن الرب يعلم أيضاً البهجة والفرحة
of the human spirit, as well.
الخاصتين بالروح البشرية أيضاً.
We want a God who can weep with those who weep,
نريد ربأً يستطيع أن يبكي مع الذين يبكون,
and rejoice with those who rejoice.
ويبتهج مع المبتهجين.
This seems to me both a deeply moving and a convincing re-statement
يبدو هذا بالنسبة لي مؤثراً للغاية وإعادة صياغة مقنعة
of Christian belief about God.
للمفهوم المسيحي عن الرب.
For hundreds of years, the prevailing orthodoxy, the accepted truth,
لمئات من السنين, كان الرأي السائد والحقيقة المقبولة
was that God the Father, the Creator, is unchanging
هي أن الرب الأب الخالق لا يتغير
and therefore by definition cannot feel pain or sadness.
ونتيجة لهذا فهو بطبيعة الحال لا يمكن أن يشعر بالألم أو الحزن
Now the unchanging God feels a bit cold and indifferent to me.
الآن أشعر أن الرب بمفهومه غير المتغير بارد إلى حد ما وغير مراعي.
And the devastating events of the 20th century
لقد أجبرت الأحداث الكارثية للقرن العشرين
have forced people to question the cold, unfeeling God.
الناس على أن يتساءلوا عن الرب بمفهومه القاسي عديم الشعور.
The slaughter of millions in the trenches and in the death camps
إن المذابح التي حدثت للملايين في الخنادق ومعسكرات الموت
have caused people to ask, "Where is God in all this?
جعلت الناس تتساءل, أين الرب من هذا كله؟
Who is God in all this?"
من هو الرب إن كان هذا هو الحال؟
And the answer was, "God is in this with us,
والإجابة أن "الرب معنا في هذا,
or God doesn't deserve our allegiance anymore."
أو أن الرب لا يستحق ولاءنا بعد الآن".
If God is a bystander, observing but not involved,
إذا ما كان الرب شاهداً, يلاحظ ولا يتدخل,
then God may well exist, but we don't want to know about Him.
إذا, فقد يكون الرب موجوداً لكننا لن نرغب في معرفته.
Many Jews and Christians now feel like this, I know.
أنا أعرف أن الكثيرين من المسيحيين واليهود يشعرون بهذا الآن.
And I am among them.
وأنا واحد منهم.
So we have a suffering God --
إن نؤمن برب معذب
a God who is intimately connected with this world and with every living soul.
رب مرتبط بهذا العالم وبكل روح حية بشكل حميمي.
I very much relate to this idea of God.
أنا مؤمن بفكرة وجود الرب
But it isn't enough. I need to ask some more questions,
لكن هذا لا يكفي. فأنا أحتاج لأن أطرح المزيد من الأسئلة,
and I hope they are questions that you will want to ask, as well,
وأتمنى أن تكون أسئلتي أسئلة ترغبون في طرحها أيضاً
some of you.
على بعض منكم.
Over the last few weeks I have been struck by the number of times
خلال الأسابيع القليلة الماضية, فوجئت بعدد المرات
that words in our worship have felt a bit inappropriate, a bit dodgy.
التي شعرت فيها بأن الكلمات في عباداتنا غير مناسبة إلى حد ما, مخادعة بعض الشيء.
We have a pram service on Tuesday mornings for mums and their pre-school children.
في صباح الثلاثاء من كل أسبوع يكون لدينا دروساً للأمهات وأطفالهم الذين لم يدخلوا المدرسة بعد.
And last week we sang with the children one of their favorite songs,
وفي الأسبوع الماضي غنينا مع الأطفال واحدة من أغنياتهم المفضلة,
"The Wise Man Built His House Upon the Rock."
"بنى الحكيم بيته على الصخرة".
Perhaps some of you know it. Some of the words go like this:
ربما يعرفها بعضكم. كلماتها كالتالي:
"The foolish man built his house upon the sand /
"بنى الغبي بيته على الرمال/
And the floods came up / And the house on the sand went crash."
وجاء المد عاتياً/ وتحطم البيت الذي على الرمال".
Then in the same week, at a funeral,
بعدها في نفس الأسبوع, بينما كنا في جنازة,
we sang the familiar hymn "We Plow the Fields and Scatter,"
كنا نغني الترنيمة المعروفة "نحرث الحقول, ونرمي البذور"
a very English hymn.
وهي ترنيمة إنجليزية حتى النخاع.
In the second verse comes the line, "The wind and waves obey Him."
في المقطع الثاني يأتي السطر: "تطيعه الرياح والأمواج".
Do they? I don't feel we can sing that song again in church,
هل هذا حقيقي؟ لا أشعر أنه يمكننا أن نغني هذه الأغنية مرة أخرى في الكنيسة,
after what's happened.
بعدما حدث.
So the first big question is about control.
لذا فالسؤال الأول الهام يدور حول السيطرة.
Does God have a plan for each of us? Is God in control?
هل لدى الرب خطة لكل واحد منا؟ هل الرب مسيطر على كل شيء؟
Does God order each moment? Does the wind and the waves obey Him?
هل يصدر الرب الأوامر في كل لحظة؟ هل تطيعه الرياح والأمواج؟
From time to time,
بين الحين والآخر,
one hears Christians telling the story of how God organized things for them,
نسمع مسيحيين يحكون قصة عن الطريقة التي رتب الرب بها الأمور لأجلهم,
so that everything worked out all right --
مما جعل كل شيء على ما يرام.
some difficulty overcome, some illness cured, some trouble averted,
فتم التغلب على بعض المصاعب, أو تم علاج مرض ما, أو تم تجنب مصيبة ما,
a parking space found at a crucial time.
أو تم العثور على مساحة انتظار للسيارة في وقت عصيب.
I can remember someone saying this to me,
أتذكر أن واحدة قالت لي هذا,
with her eyes shining with enthusiasm at this wonderful confirmation of her faith
وعيناها تشعان بالحماس نتيجة هذا التأكيد الرائع لإيمانها
and the goodness of God.
ولطيبة الرب
But if God can or will do these things --
لكن إذا كان الرب يستطيع أن يفعل أو سيفعل مثل هذه الأشياء --
intervene to change the flow of events --
أن يتدخل فيغير مسار الأحداث --
then surely he could have stopped the tsunami.
فمن المؤكد أنه كان يستطيع أن يوقف التسونامي.
Do we have a local God who can do little things like parking spaces,
هل لدينا رب جزئي يستطيع القيام بأشياء صغيرة مثل إيجاد مساحات انتظار للسيارات,
but not big things like 500 mile-per-hour waves?
لكنه لا يفعل الأشياء الكبيرة مثل إيقاف أمواج تسير بسرعة 500 ميلاً في الساعة؟
That's just not acceptable to intelligent Christians,
ليس هذا بالأمر المقبول لدى المسيحيين الأذكياء,
and we must acknowledge it.
وينبغي أن نعترف بذلك.
Either God is responsible for the tsunami,
إما أن الرب مسئول عن التسونامي,
or God is not in control.
أو أنه لا يسيطر على الأمور.
After the tragedy, survival stories began to emerge.
بعد المأساة, بدأت قصص النجاة في الظهور,
You probably heard some of them:
ربما تكونوا قد سمعتم بعض هذه القصص.
the man who surfed the wave,
الرجل الذي تزلج على الأمواج.
the teenage girl who recognized the danger
المراهقة التي تنبأت بالخطر
because she had just been learning about tsunamis at school.
لأنها كانت قد تعلمت درساً عن التسونامي لتوها في المدرسة.
Then there was the congregation who had left their usual church building on the shore
وهناك جماعة المصلين الذين تركوا مبنى الكنيسة المعتاد الموجود على الشاطيء
to hold a service in the hills.
للصلاة على التلال.
The preacher delivered an extra long sermon,
وألقى الخطيب عظة طويلة للغاية,
so that they were still out of harm's way when the wave struck.
وبالتالي كانوا بعيدين عن الضرر عندما عتت الأمواج.
Afterwards someone said that God must have been looking after them.
بعد ذلك قال أحدهم إنه لابد وأن الرب كان يرعاهم.
So the next question is about partiality.
لذا فالسؤال التالي عن الجزئية.
Can we earn God's favor by worshipping Him or believing in Him?
هل يمكننا أن نحصل على تأييد الرب لنا من خلال عبادته أو الإيمان به؟
Does God demand loyalty, like any medieval tyrant?
هل يطلب الرب منا الولاء, مثل أي طاغية في العصور الوسطى؟
A God who looks after His own, so that Christians are OK,
رب يعتني بعباده, مما يجعل المسيحيين بخير حال,
while everyone else perishes?
بينما يفنى الباقون؟
A cosmic us and them, and a God who is guilty of the worst kind of favoritism?
إننا نعيش في نفس الكون, فهل يرتكب الرب أسوأ أنواع المحسوبية؟
That would be appalling,
سيكون هذا صادماً,
and that would be the point at which I would hand in my membership.
وسيكون هو الأمر الذي سأتخلى فيه عن كهانتي.
Such a God would be morally inferior to the highest ideals of humanity.
فمثل هذا الرب سيكون من الناحية الخلقية أدنى من المثل العليا البشرية.
So who is God, if not the great puppet-master or the tribal protector?
إذا, من هو الرب إن لم يكن محرك عرائس عظيم أو حامي حمى القبيلة البشرية؟
Perhaps God allows or permits terrible things to happen,
ربما يسمح الرب أو يجيز حدوث أشياء فظيعة,
so that heroism and compassion can be shown.
حتى تظهر البطولة والرأفة.
Perhaps God is testing us: testing our charity, or our faith.
ربما يختبرنا الرب, يختبر محبتنا أو إيماننا.
Perhaps there is a great, cosmic plan that allows for horrible suffering
ربما تكون هناك خطة كونية عظيمة تسمح بوجود معاناة هائلة
so that everything will work out OK in the end.
كي ينتهي كل شيء إلى خير حال في النهاية.
Perhaps, but these ideas are all just variations on God controlling everything,
ربما, لكن كل هذه الأفكار هي مجرد تنويعات لمفهوم الرب الذي يسيطر على كل شيء.
the supreme commander toying with expendable units in a great campaign.
إنه القائد العظيم يلهو بأشياء لا قيمة لها في حدث عظيم.
We are still left with a God who can do the tsunami and allow Auschwitz.
إننا مازلنا في النهاية أمام رب يمكنه أن يقوم بالتسونامي أو بمعسكرات أوشفيتز.
In his great novel, "The Brothers Karamazov," Dostoevsky gives these words to Ivan,
في روايته العظيمة "الإخوة كارامازوف" يكتب دوستويفسكي هذه الكلمات على لسان إيفان,
addressed to his naive and devout younger brother, Alyosha:
موجهة لأخيه الأصغر الساذج المتدين أليوشا:
"If the sufferings of children go to make up the sum of sufferings
"لو أن معاناة الأطفال جُمعت فساوت مجموع المعاناة
which is necessary for the purchase of truth,
اللازمة لشراء الحقيقة,
then I say beforehand that the entire truth is not worth such a price.
فأنا أقول لك مقدماً أن الحقيقة بأكملها لا تستحق مثل هذا الثمن.
We cannot afford to pay so much for admission.
لا يمكننا أن ننفق كل هذا من أجل الدخول في معية الرب.
It is not God that I do not accept.
ليس الرب هو ما لا أقبله.
I merely, most respectfully, return Him the ticket."
لكنني وبكل احترام سأعيد له تذكرة الدخول فحسب".
Or perhaps God set the whole universe going at the beginning
أو ربما جعل الرب العالم بأكمله يرتد إلى البداية
and then relinquished control forever,
ثم تخلى عن السيطرة عليه إلى الأبد,
so that natural processes could occur, and evolution run its course.
وبالتالي تستطيع العمليات الطبيعية أن تحدث ويمكن للنشوء والارتقاء أن يتخذا مساريهما
This seems more acceptable,
يبدو هذا مقبولاً بدرجة أكبر,
but it still leaves God with the ultimate moral responsibility.
لكن تبقى على كاهل الرب المسئولية الخلقية المطلقة.
Is God a cold, unfeeling spectator?
هل الرب مراقب قاس وغير مبالي؟
Or a powerless lover, watching with infinite compassion
أم أنه محب لا حيلة له يشاهد بشفقة مطلقة
things God is unable to control or change?
الأشياء التي لا يستطيع التحكم فيها أو تغييرها؟
Is God intimately involved in our suffering,
هل يشاركنا الرب بحميمية معاناتنا,
so that He feels it in His own being?
فيشعر بها داخله؟
If we believe something like this, we must let go of the puppet-master completely,
إذا كنا نؤمن بشيء من هذا القبيل فلابد أن نتخلى عن مفهوم الرب محرك العرائس بشكل كلي,
take our leave of the almighty controller, abandon traditional models.
ونتخلى عن مفهوم الرب المسيطر, ونهجر المفاهيم التقليدية للرب.
We must think again about God.
ينبغي علينا أن نفكر مرة أخرى في الرب.
Maybe God doesn't do things at all.
ربما لا يفعل الرب الأشياء على الإطلاق.
Maybe God isn't an agent like all of us are agents.
قد لا يكون الرب مسبباً للأشياء مثلما نفعل نحن.
Early religious thought conceived God as a sort of superhuman person,
لقد أدرك الفكر الديني الأول الرب على أنه شخص ذو قدرات تفوق البشر.
doing things all over the place.
يسبب الأشياء في كل مكان.
Beating up the Egyptians, drowning them in the Red Sea, wasting cities, getting angry.
فهو يهزم الفراعنة بإغراقهم في البحر الأحمر, ويدمر المدن, ويثور.
The people knew their God by His mighty acts.
كان الناس يعرفون ربهم من خلال أفعاله الجبارة.
But what if God doesn't act? What if God doesn't do things at all?
لكن ماذا لو كان الرب لا يقوم بأي دور؟ ماذا لو أن الرب لا يفعل الأشياء على الإطلاق؟
What if God is in things?
ماذا لو كان الرب في الأشياء؟
The loving soul of the universe.
روح الكون المحبة.
An in-dwelling compassionate presence, underpinning and sustaining all things.
وجود حان مقيم يعزز ويؤيد كل الأشياء.
What if God is in things?
ماذا لو كان الرب في الأشياء؟
In the infinitely complex network of relationships and connections that make up life.
في شبكة العلاقات والروابط المعقدة التي تصنع الحياة.
In the natural cycle of life and death,
في الدورة الطبيعية للحياة والموت,
the creation and destruction that must happen continuously.
الخلق والدمار اللذان ينبغيا أن يحدثا بشكل مستمر.
In the process of evolution.
في عملية النشوء والارتقاء.
In the incredible intricacy and magnificence of the natural world.
في التعقيد والعظمة المذهلين للعالم الطبيعي.
In the collective unconscious, the soul of the human race.
في اللاوعي الجمعي, في روح الجنس البشري.
In you, in me, mind and body and spirit.
فيك, وفي, عقلاً وجسداً وروحاً.
In the tsunami, in the victims. In the depth of things.
في التسونامي, في الضحايا. في أعماق الأشياء.
In presence and in absence. In simplicity and complexity.
في الحضور والغياب. في البساطة والتعقيد.
In change and development and growth.
في التغير والتطور والنماء.
How does this in-ness, this innerness, this interiority of God work?
كيف تعمل هذه الكينونة الداخلية الخاصة بالرب؟
It's hard to conceive, and begs more questions.
من الصعب أن ندرك ذلك, غير أن هذا يقودنا إلى المزيد من الأسئلة.
Is God just another name for the universe,
هل الرب مسمى آخر للكون فحسب,
with no independent existence at all?
بلا أي وجود مستقل له على الإطلاق؟
I don't know.
لا أعرف
To what extent can we ascribe personality to God?
إلى أي مدى يمكن أن نجزم بهوية الرب؟
In the end, we have to say, "I don't know."
في النهاية, ينبغي علينا أن نقول, "أنا لا أعرف".
If we knew, God would not be God.
فإذا ما كنا نعرف, لما كان الرب هو الرب.
To have faith in this God
إن الإيمان بهذا الرب
would be more like trusting an essential benevolence in the universe,
سيكون أشبه بالثقة في وجود نزعة أساسية نحو الخير في الكون
and less like believing a system of doctrinal statements.
وأبعد كثيراً عن الإيمان بنظام من النصوص العقائدية.
Isn't it ironic that Christians who claim to believe
ألا يثير السخرية أن المسيحيين الذين يزعمون أنهم يؤمنون
in an infinite, unknowable being
بكيان مطلق وغير معروف
then tie God down in closed systems and rigid doctrines?
يحصرون الرب في نظم مغلقة وعقائد جامدة؟
How could one practice such a faith?
كيف يمكن للمرء أن يمارس مثل هذا الإيمان؟
By seeking the God within. By cultivating my own inwardness.
من خلال البحث عن الرب داخلنا. من خلال تنمية الكينونة الداخلية لدينا.
In silence, in meditation, in my inner space, in the me that remains
في الهدوء, في التأمل, في الحيز الداخلي الخاص بي, في الجانب الخالد مني
when I gently put aside my passing emotions and ideas and preoccupations.
عندما أنحي جانباً مشاعري وأفكاري وانشغالاتي العابرة.
In awareness of the inner conversation.
في وعيي بحديثي الداخلي.
And how would we live such a faith? How would I live such a faith?
كيف يمكن لنا أن نعيش مثل هذا الإيمان؟ كيف يمكن لي أن أعيش مثل هذا الإيمان؟
By seeking intimate connection with your inwardness.
من خلال البحث عن رابط حميمي بيني وبين كينونتي الداخلية.
The kind of relationships when deep speaks to deep.
ذلك النوع من العلاقة التي تتحدث فيه أعماقي لأعماقي.
If God is in all people, then there is a meeting place
لو أن الرب موجود في كل الناس, فهناك مكان التقاء إذاً
where my relationship with you becomes a three-way encounter.
حيث تصبح علاقتي بك التقاء ثلاثي الأطراف.
There is an Indian greeting, which I'm sure some of you know:
هناك تحية هندية أنا متأكد من أن بعضكم يعرفها:
"Namaste," accompanied by a respectful bow,
"ناماستاى" وتصاحبها انحناءة احترام,
which, roughly translated means,
وهي تعني إذا ما ترجمت بشكل تقريبي
"That which is of God in me greets that which of God is in you."
"ما بداخلي من الرب يلقي التحية على ما بداخلك منه"
Namaste.
ناماستاى
And how would one deepen such a faith?
كيف يمكن للمرء أن يعمق مثل هذا الإيمان؟
By seeking the inwardness which is in all things.
من خلال البحث عن الكينونة الداخلية الموجودة في كل الأشياء.
In music and poetry, in the natural world of beauty
في الموسيقى والشعر, في العالم الطبيعي للجمال
and in the small ordinary things of life,
وفي الأشياء الصغيرة العادية الموجودة بالحياة,
there is a deep, indwelling presence that makes them extraordinary.
هناك كيان عميق ومقيم يجعل هذه الأشياء مدهشة.
It needs a profound attentiveness and a patient waiting,
إن هذا البحث يتطلب يقظة كبيرة وانتظاراً صبوراً.
a contemplative attitude and a generosity and openness
توجهاً تأملياً, وسماحة وانفتاحاً
to those whose experience is different from my own.
على هؤلاء الذين تختلف خبراتهم عن خبراتي.
When I stood up to speak to my people about God and the tsunami,
عندما وقفت كي أتحدث إلى المصلين عن الرب وتسونامي,
I had no answers to offer them.
لم يكن لدي إجابات أقدمها لهم.
No neat packages of faith, with Bible references to prove them.
لم يكن لدي عبارات منمقة من الإيمان أقدمها لهم مع دلائل تثبتها من الكتاب المقدس.
Only doubts and questioning and uncertainty.
كان لدي فقط شكوك وتساؤلات وارتياب.
I had some suggestions to make --
كان لدي بعض الاقتراحات,
possible new ways of thinking about God.
اقتراحات عن طرق جديدة للتفكير في الرب.
Ways that might allow us to go on, down a new and uncharted road.
طرق يمكن أن تسمح لنا بالاستمرار, والمضي على طريق جديد وغير معلوم.
But in the end, the only thing I could say for sure was, "I don't know,"
لكن في النهاية, كان الشيء الوحيد الذي استطعت قوله بكل تأكيد هو "لا أعرف",
and that just might be the most profoundly religious statement of all.
وربما تكون هذه هي الجملة الدينية الأكثر عمقاً على الإطلاق.
Thank you.
أشكركم.